Guide to the Philip Everett Curtiss Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Philip Everett Curtiss papers
1901-1944
YCAL MSS 443
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
13.65
(32 boxes)
The Philip Everett Curtiss papers contain writings, printed material, correspondence, and other materials documenting the literary career of Connecticut native Philip Everett Curtiss. Writings consist chiefly of drafts for novels and shorter works, such as articles. Printed materials include journals and clippings containing printed versions of writings by Curtiss and material by, about, and relating to Curtiss. Correspondence consists chiefly of incoming correspondence from publishers, further documenting his literary career. Personal papers include a small number of books inscribed to Curtiss, contracts, manuscript notes, and photographs.
Curtiss, Philip, 1885-1964
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited by Philip Everett Curtiss prior to his death in 1964. Gift of Anne Scoville, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Miscrofilm available for portions of the collection.
Philip Everett Curtiss (1885-1964)
Philip Everett Curtiss, novelist, legislator, and justice. After a brief career as a newspaper reporter on The Hartford Courant and The Hartford Times, Curtiss returned to his family home in Norfolk, Connecticut, to write. His novels include Between Two Worlds (1916), Mummers in Mufti (1922) and The Gay Conspirators (1924). He turned to politics and law later in life, representing his home district in the General Assembly, as a Republican, from 1941 to 1947 and serving as a trial justice from 1940 to 1955.
Biographical information taken from obituary, New York Times (1923-Current file); May 25, 1964; ProQuest Historical Newspapers (accessed 2 March 2011).
Scope and Contents
The Philip Everett Curtiss papers contain writings, printed material, correspondence, and other materials documenting the literary career of Connecticut native Philip Everett Curtiss. Writings consist chiefly of drafts for novels and shorter works, such as articles. Printed materials include journals and clippings containing printed versions of writings by Curtiss and material by, about, and relating to Curtiss. Correspondence consists chiefly of incoming correspondence from publishers, further documenting his literary career. Personal papers include a small number of books inscribed to Curtiss, contracts, manuscript notes, and photographs.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Writings, 1907-1944. II. Printed Materials, 1901-1940. III. Correspondence, 1903-1932. IV. Personal Papers, 1916-1932.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Authors; Curtiss, Philip, 1885-1964
- Writings, 1907-1944; Series I; 7.3; (18 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Writings contains drafts of writings by Curtiss. There are drafts for several novels and for numerous shorter works, chiefly articles. Many shorter works appear on personal letterhead from "809 Asylum Avenue, Hartford, Conn.", presumably dating from his early career as a newspaper reporter, whereas many others are marked from his hometown of Norfolk, where he settled later. A considerable amount of unsorted writings can be found at the end of the alphabetical run of titles and additional writings, also not identified by title, can be found in Series II. Printed Materials.
  - "Adventures of a Writer's Life", undated (Box 1)
  - "Ah, Bold Young Lochinvar", undated (Box 1)
  - "And West Is West", undated (Box 1)
  - " The Ankoond of Swat", undated (Box 1)
  - "Anonymous '71", 1925 (Box 1)
  - "Araminta's Polo Team", undated (Box 1)
  - " The Archbishop's Overshoes", undated (Box 1)
  - " Are You Satisfied With Your Name?", undated (Box 1)
  - "Are You Thirty-Five?", undated (Box 1)
  - " The Assault and Capture of Pettigard's Tavern", undated (Box 1)
  - "A Backhand Prodigal", undated (Box 1)
  - "Bellsmith", undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - "A Bench at the Fair", undated (Box 1)
  - Between Two Worlds, undated (Box 1)
  - Between Two Worlds, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Blood of Heroes", undated (Box 2)
  - "The Book-Worm", undated (Box 2)
  - "The Bow-Legs of Destiny", undated (Box 2)
  - "Brother Kemp From...", undated (Box 2)
  - "Bugs", undated (Box 2)
  - "The Bungalow", [circa 1913]; 3 (Box 2)
  - "Calm Yourself Sweetheart: Weren't You Ever a Mother Yourself?", undated (Box 2)
  - " Captain Marcy's Last Run", undated (Box 2)
  - "A Castillian Clubman", undated (Box 2)
  - "Castles in Spain", [192?] (Box 2)
  - "Chivalry and the Eight-hour Day", undated (Box 2)
  - "Cold Hands and a Warm Heart", undated (Box 2)
  - "Comes Dora", undated (Box 3)
  - "The Comic Element in Sex", undated (Box 3)
  - "The Conquest of Richard the Silent", undated (Box 3)
  - "The County Constable", undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - "The Country Garageman", undated (Box 3)
  - Crater's Gold, undated; 4 (Box 3)
  - "The Crocodile's Half Sister, Louise", undated (Box 3)
  - "The Devil His Due", undated (Box 3)
  - "The Dogs of War", undated (Box 3)
  - "The Double Demise of Mrs. McCarthy", undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - "The Elixir of Lies", undated (Box 3)
  - "The Emancipation of the Buick", undated (Box 3)
  - "Emily's Trunk -- A New Force in Our National Life", undated (Box 3)
  - "The English Country Life Myth", undated (Box 4)
  - "The Equestrian Order", undated (Box 4)
  - "An Esau of the Mountains", undated (Box 4)
  - "Essays in Idleness", undated (Box 4)
  - "The Extravagance of Economy", undated (Box 4)
  - "Eyes They Have", undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - "The Fancy Skater of Melonmerang", undated (Box 4)
  - "A Few Blows in Defense of a Lady", undated (Box 4)
  - "The Fight to the Brave", undated (Box 4)
  - "The Final Game and the Final Goals", undated (Box 4)
  - "The First of the Cuties", undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - "The Flatness of Truth", undated (Box 4)
  - "A Flier in Learning", undated (Box 4)
  - "Forty-five", undated (Box 4)
  - The Gay Conspirators, 1924 (Box 4)
  - "The Genii of Lutton's Hill", undated (Box 4)
  - ""Gertrude" Brown", undated (Box 5)
  - "The Girl in Black", undated (Box 5)
  - "The Golden Calf", undated; 3 (Box 5)
  - "Grandpa Kept Warm", undated (Box 5)
  - "The Great American Ladder", undated; 3 (Box 5)
  - "Gum-Shoes", undated (Box 5)
  - "Guns", undated (Box 5)
  - "Henry W. Longfellow", undated (Box 5)
  - "The Highboy", undated (Box 5)
  - "The Holy Roman Empire of the Bronx", undated (Box 5)
  - The Honorable Charley, undated (Box 5)
  - "The Horsey Man", undated (Box 5)
  - "How Did They Do It?", undated (Box 5)
  - "Hungarian - 28- Defective", undated (Box 5)
  - "I Am the Original Hick", undated (Box 6)
  - "I Was One of the Kids From Rag Alley", undated (Box 6)
  - "In Love and War", undated (Box 6)
  - "In the Billiard Room", undated (Box 6)
  - "The Intermediary", undated (Box 6)
  - "The Iron Boy", undated (Box 6)
  - "Is Fame Becoming Extinct?", undated (Box 6)
  - "It Was Written in Galt", undated (Box 6)
  - "Jack Harker Yalevard", undated (Box 6)
  - "The John Doe Law in American Fiction", undated (Box 6)
  - "The King of Borrachia", undated (Box 6)
  - "The Knight of the Bath", undated (Box 6)
  - The Ladder, undated; 4 (Box 6)
  - The Ladder, galley proof, undated (Box 7)
  - "Lady, Lady, Little Lady", undated (Box 7)
  - "The Left-Handed Piccolo Player", undated (Box 7)
  - "Let's Do Over the Parlor", undated (Box 7)
  - "The Life and Times of Pentelicus the Younger", undated (Box 7)
  - "Lights at Sea", undated; 2 (Box 7)
  - "Lionel", undated (Box 7)
  - "The Little Black Sheep", undated (Box 7)
  - "The Little Black Sheep", undated; 2 (Box 8)
  - "The Long Game and the Final Goal", undated (Box 8)
  - "The Lost Art of Drinking Too Much", undated (Box 8)
  - "Love Lyrics of an Idiot", undated (Box 8)
  - "The Love Story of a Factory Town", undated (Box 8)
  - "A Love Story of the Fourth Class", undated (Box 8)
  - "The Lure of the Handbook", undated (Box 8)
  - "The Mad Chauffeur", undated (Box 8)
  - "Man and Beast", undated; 2 (Box 8)
  - "The Man in the Brand New Derby", undated (Box 8)
  - The Man Who Knew Life, undated (Box 8)
  - "The Man Who Tried Hard to be Human", undated (Box 8)
  - "A Man Who Went Forward by Going Backward", undated (Box 8)
  - "The Man Who Would be Vulgar", undated (Box 8)
  - "Marked Personal", undated (Box 8)
  - "The Master Stroke", undated; 2 (Box 8)
  - "The Men Who Never Marry", undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - "The Monster", undated (Box 9)
  - "Motor Fear and How to Cure It", undated (Box 9)
  - "Mrs. Hopple and Daughter", undated (Box 9)
  - "The Mucker Pose", undated (Box 9)
  - Mummers in Mufti, galley proof, undated (Box 9)
  - "My Courtship and Its Consequences", undated (Box 9)
  - "The Mystery of the Missing Monocle", 1914, undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - "Neither Do They Spin", undated (Box 9)
  - "New-Mown Hay", undated (Box 9)
  - "The Non-Existence of the Obvious", undated (Box 9)
  - "Nothing But Hicks", undated (Box 9)
  - "The Odds On: A Short Story", undated; 3 (Box 9)
  - "Of Bad Tempers", undated (Box 9)
  - "Old Polly", undated (Box 9)
  - "On the British Left", undated (Box 9)
  - "On the Circuit", undated (Box 9)
  - "One Hundred Years of Joan", undated (Box 9)
  - "One Smith", undated (Box 9)
  - "The Other Side", undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - "Our Wives and Daughters", undated (Box 10)
  - "Out of Nazareth", undated; 3 (Box 10)
  - An Outline of Government in Connecticut, 1944 (Box 10)
  - "The Party of the Third Part", undated (Box 10)
  - "The Patrician", undated (Box 10)
  - "A Penny in the Wide", undated (Box 10)
  - "A Plea for the Old Fashioned Sunday", undated (Box 10)
  - "Plus Fours", undated (Box 10)
  - "A Polo Proxy", undated (Box 10)
  - "Popette", undated (Box 10)
  - "The Poppycock of Manual Labor", undated (Box 10)
  - "The Postmaster General of Mindanao", undated (Box 10)
  - "Pounds, Shillings, and Pence", undated (Box 10)
  - "Prince Charming, PhD", undated (Box 10)
  - "The Punch", undated (Box 10)
  - "The Quick and the Living", undated (Box 10)
  - "Reddy Reverts to Type", undated (Box 11)
  - "The Return of Medicine Men", undated (Box 11)
  - "The Right of Way", undated (Box 11)
  - "Riparian Rights", undated (Box 11)
  - "Shaw's Real Weakness", undated (Box 11)
  - "The Shears of Delilah", undated (Box 11)
  - "Sherrard O'Connor", undated (Box 11)
  - "The Shocking Fate of Sir Willoughy Stubbs", undated; 3 (Box 11)
  - "The Sisters", undated (Box 11)
  - "The Six Surviving Sins", undated (Box 11)
  - "A Slack Year in Piracy", undated; 2 (Box 11)
  - "Soldiering for a Livelihood", undated; 2 (Box 11)
  - "Special Sunday Story", undated (Box 11)
  - "A Splendid Heroine", undated (Box 11)
  - "The Stars in Their Orbits", undated (Box 11)
  - "The Story of a Snail", undated; 2 (Box 11)
  - "Student Days in Modern Spain", 1907, undated (Box 11)
  - "Student Life in Spain", undated (Box 11)
  - "A Study in the Third Degree", undated (Box 11)
  - "Summer Folks", undated (Box 11)
  - "Sylvia Goes to the City", undated (Box 11)
  - "The Tale of a Shoe", undated (Box 11)
  - "The Tango Trust", undated (Box 11)
  - "The Technique Bugaboo", undated (Box 11)
  - "Temperament", undated (Box 12)
  - "That Little Miss Gray", undated (Box 12)
  - "Third Wife of Andronicus Ashley", undated (Box 12)
  - "Thirty-five: The Second Lap of Life", undated (Box 12)
  - "Thoreau", undated (Box 12)
  - "Those Things Which Aren't Caeser's", undated (Box 12)
  - "Three Drops and a Slice of Lemon", undated (Box 12)
  - "To the Editor of The Tripod", undated (Box 12)
  - "To-night C-24-R", undated (Box 12)
  - "The Transmigration of Horace", undated (Box 12)
  - "The Ultra Mrs. Manty", undated (Box 12)
  - "Vive Le Quartier!", undated; 2 (Box 12)
  - Wanted: A Fool, 1919, undated; 3 (Box 12)
  - "Watching Broadway From a Farmhouse Window", undated (Box 12)
  - "The Waving Palm and the Blue Lagoon", undated (Box 12)
  - "When Artie Came Marching Home", undated (Box 12)
  - "When Is a Ford Not a Ford", undated (Box 12)
  - "When the Ashes Turn Pure White", undated (Box 13)
  - "White Ashes", undated (Box 13)
  - "Why I Am Not Shakespeare", undated (Box 13)
  - "Why I Prefer to Live in "'The Sticks'", undated (Box 13)
  - "Wordsworth as a Nature Poet", undated (Box 13)
  - "The Worldings", undated (Box 13)
  - Unidentified and unsorted writings, 1934, undated; 13 (Box 13)
  - Unidentified and unsorted writings, 1927, undated; 7 (Box 14)
  - Unidentified and unsorted writings, 1914-1921, undated; 5 (Box 15)
  - Unidentified and unsorted writings, 1912, undated; 8 (Box 16)
  - Unidentified and unsorted writings, 1925-1928, undated; 5 (Box 17)
  - Unidentified and unsorted writings, 1925, undated; 3 (Box 18)
- Printed Material, 1901-1940; Series II; 3.13; (8 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: Journals and Clippings.
  Series II. Printed Materials contains journals and clippings. The journals, arranged alphabetically by title, appear to contain printed versions of writings by Curtiss, whereas the clippings contain material by, about, and relating to Curtiss. For example, there are short writings by Curtiss, reviews of his work by others, brief mentions, and clippings on other topics. Clippings are unsorted.
  - Journals
    - The American Magazine, 1911-1916; 7 (Box 19)
    - The American Magazine, 1916 (Box 20)
    - The Atlantic Monthly, 1935 October; 2 (Box 20)
    - The Bookman, 1915 May (Box 20)
    - The Century, 1913 October (Box 20)
    - The Chronicle, 1901-1902 (Box 20)
    - Collier's, 1912 November 16
    - The Country Home, 1936 January (Box 20)
    - Every Week, 1915-1918
    - Everybody's Magazine, 1911, 1913; 2 (Box 20)
    - Everybody's Magazine, 1913 (Box 21)
    - Harper's Monthly Magazine, 1917-1918; 4 (Box 21)
    - Harper's Monthly Magazine, 1919-1931; 6 (Box 22)
    - Harper's Monthly Magazine, 1939-1940; 2 (Box 23)
    - Harper's Weekly, 1914 March 7 (Box 23)
    - The Ladies' Home Journal, 1925 September
    - Das Leben, 1931 February (Box 23)
    - McClure's Magazine, 1912 May (Box 23)
    - Der Querschnitt, 1931 February (Box 23)
    - The Popular Magazine, 1916 October 7 (Box 23)
    - Reader's Digest, 1938 July (Box 23)
    - The Red Book Magazine, 1919 May (Box 23)
    - The Saturday Evening Post, 1912-1937
    - Scribner's Magazine, 1914; 2 (Box 23)
    - Scribner's Magazine, 1919, 1925 (Box 24)
    - The Smart Set, 1912, 1916; 5 (Box 24)
    - Sunday Magazine of the New York Tribune, 1914 January 25; Stored in: Oversize, Box 32
    - The Trinity Tablet, 1903 (Box 25)
    - Vanity Fair, 1918
    - Women's Home Companion, 1930 October
    - Yankee, 1936 October (Box 25)
  - Clippings
    - Unsorted clippings, [circa 1906-1918]; 6 (Box 25)
    - Unsorted clippings, [circa 1916-1918] (Box 26)
- Correspondence, 1903-1932; Series III; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Series III. Correspondence appears to consist chiefly of incoming correspondence from publishers, with letters from many of the publishers represented in Series II. Printed Material, including but not limited to The American Magazine, Collier's, Everybody's Magazine, and Harper's. Correspondence is unsorted, with a good portion, if not the bulk, still in original envelopes.
  - Unsorted correspondence, [circa 1911-1931]; 5 (Box 27)
  - Unsorted correspondence, [circa 1903-1932]; 6 (Box 28)
  - Unsorted correspondence, [circa 1911-1916]; 6 (Box 29)
- Personal Papers, 1916-1932; Series IV; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Series IV. Personal Papers contains books inscribed to Curtiss, contracts with publishers, notes and notebooks, and photographs.
  - Books inscribed to Curtiss, 1930-1932, undated; 4 (Box 30)
  - Contracts, 1916-1929 (Box 31)
  - Notebook and notes, undated; 2 (Box 31)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 31)
- Oversize, 1912-1937; 1.34; (1 box)
  - Collier's (In Series II), 1912 November 16 (Box 32)
  - Every Week (In Series II), 1915-1918 (Box 32)
  - The Ladies' Home Journal (In Series II), 1925 September (Box 32)
  - The Saturday Evening Post (In Series II), 1912-1937; 4 (Box 32)
  - Sunday Magazine of the New York Tribune (In Series II), 1914 January 25 (Box 32)
  - Vanity Fair (In Series II), 1918 (Box 32)
  - Women's Home Companion (In Series II), 1930 October (Box 32)